<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Dreadfull newes: or A true relation of the great, violent and late earthquake Hapned the 27. day of March, stilo Romano last, at Callabria, in the kingdome of Naples, about the houres of three and foure in the afternoone, to the over-throw and ruine of many cities, townes, and castles, and the death of above fifty thousand persons. With the names of the principall of the sayd cities, townes and castles, destroyed by the said earthquake, according to the originall printed and published by authority at Venice. Published with license and authority.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1638</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 15 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 10 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A17541</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 4349.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S113989</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99849217</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99849217</idno>
            <idno type="VID">14355</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A17541)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 14355)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1180:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Dreadfull newes: or A true relation of the great, violent and late earthquake Hapned the 27. day of March, stilo Romano last, at Callabria, in the kingdome of Naples, about the houres of three and foure in the afternoone, to the over-throw and ruine of many cities, townes, and castles, and the death of above fifty thousand persons. With the names of the principall of the sayd cities, townes and castles, destroyed by the said earthquake, according to the originall printed and published by authority at Venice. Published with license and authority.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 17, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by I. Okes, for R. Mab,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1638.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Erroneously attributed to Martin Parker.</note>
                  <note>Variant: an earlier state; imprint has "Mabb"; part of heading on A2r and all of the page numbers in another setting.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 19229 on UMI microfilm.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Calabria (Italy) --  History --  Earthquake, 1638 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:14355:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:14355:1"/>
            <p> Dreadfull Newes: OR A true Relation of the Great, Violent and late <hi>Earthquake.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hapned the 27. day of <hi>March,</hi> Stilo Romano laſt, at <hi>Callabria,</hi> in the Kingdome of <hi>Naples,</hi> about the houres of three and foure in the after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noone, to the over-throw and ruine of many Cities, Townes, and Caſtles, and the death of above fifty thouſand perſons.</p>
            <p>With the names of the principall of the ſayd Cities, Townes and Caſtles, deſtroyed by the ſaid Earthquake, according to the Originall Printed and publiſhed by Authority at <hi>Venice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Publiſhed with Licenſe and Authority.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by <hi>I. Okes,</hi> for <hi>R. Mab.</hi> 1638.
<pb facs="tcp:14355:2"/>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:14355:2"/>
            <head>A True RELATION OF A GREAT and violent Earthquake happened in <hi>Callabria</hi> the 27. of <hi>March,</hi> 1638. <hi>Stilo Romano,</hi> to the overthrow of Eight great Cities, Twenty foure Townes, and about <hi>fifty Thouſand perſons.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Have oftentimes conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered with my ſelfe in the depth of my ſerious Meditations, the moſt remarkable Prodigies, and Accidents that have happened ſince the Birth of our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:14355:3"/> 
               <hi>Chriſt,</hi> to this very Time wherein wee now are: and though I confeſſe, that old Authors have left them to us in the writings both terrible and feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and ſo horrid to the Learned of thoſe times, and to the Aged of thoſe dayes, that it afforded them matter and Subiect ſufficient of relating and writing the ſame to the Ages and Times that ſhall ſucceed them, and were accompanied with ſuch terrours to thoſe that then were the Eye-wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes thereof, that the ſame cauſed them to be, as the <hi>Scripture</hi> hath it, at their wits end, and tooke from them as then, all manner of life and moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, bringing therewith to thoſe that onely heard thereof, though farre di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant, both a wonderfull amazement and an exceeding aſtoniſhment, both of body and minde: the moſt notable that have beene obſerved, have fallen out and happen'd contrary to the uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all and common courſe of Nature, as
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:14355:3"/> the apparition of many Sunnes at one and the ſelfe-ſame inſtant of time, and that happened in the yeere of our Lord 64. and in the yeere of our Lord 438. beſides the three Sunnes that appeared and was manifeſted to the view of all beholders, wherein the figure of a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked Monſter appeared, whoſe body bore three Heads of humane forme. The ſaid ſtrange Accidents in the Fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mament by the apparition of many Sunnes was alſo ſeene in the yeeres 1429, 1452, and 1480. accompani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed alwayes with horrible Tempeſts, cruell Lightnings, and with violent Thundrings and rumors in the Ayre. Beſides which, at other times were ſeene Dragons with three Heads, with many Baſilisks and flying Serpents, combatting and fighting againſt Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of Horſe and Foote, as in the yeeres of our Lord 984. and 995. At other times alſo were ſeene fiery Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars of immeaſurable greatneſſe and
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:14355:4"/> length, the moſt remarkable of which happened Twelve yeeres after the comming of our Redeemer <hi>Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus,</hi> and ſo alſo the ſame in the yeeres of 372. 1560. and 1569.</p>
            <p>Againe, at one and the ſelfe-ſame time were ſeene flying Bafilisks and ſiery Pillars, as in the yeeres of our Lord 1585. and oftentimes have been ſeene Swords, Darts, and other Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall Weapons; and armed Horſe and Foote-men which have combatted to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and have beene ſeene the one ſide to overthrow and put to rout the other, as in the yeere of our Lord 71. and in the yeere 1526.</p>
            <p>In the Iſland of <hi>Cyprus,</hi> now under the Subiection of the Grand <hi>Turke,</hi> in the yeere of our Lord 78. did appeare in the Firmament, to the terrour of the beholders, Foure men of a large ſtature and greatneſſe, cloathed with Fire, and armed with horrible Darts, and Comets: Likewiſe it is recorded
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:14355:4"/> that in <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> the <hi>Metropolis</hi> of the preſent Empire of the <hi>Turkes,</hi> in the yeere of our Lord 432. it powred downe or hailed (if I may ſo tearme it) a ſtorme of Stones: and in the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>Tolledo</hi> in <hi>Spaine</hi> in the ſame yeere was ſeene in the Ayre ſtrange Diaboli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call figures and ſhapes, which moved much the beholders both to feare and horrour.</p>
            <p>At other times have beene alſo ſeene many Croſſes in the Firmament, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times to the number of Seven and Eight, with fiery Comets, accompani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with other prodigies, and this happened in the yeere of our Lord, 1228. and 1321. and in concluſion to avoid prolixity in the recounting and numbring of ſo many ſtrange and ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible Accidents, (that Marble it ſelfe would be affraid if it were any way ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of feare and frighting) To ſee it raine a quantity of humane Corps, and to fall from the Skies to the number of
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:14355:5"/> two Hundred in one place, would doubtleſſe affright the moſt hardy and undaunted courage of the moſt reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute and valiant: and what living Soule would not be affraid thereat? and this happened in the yeere 570. in <hi>Italy,</hi> and ſome yeeres after in the Kingdome of <hi>France.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In our times to heare of <hi>Earthquakes,</hi> and ſee the motion and removall of the Land in this or in that part of the World, to ſee the Ayre infected, to feele the contagious Plague and Peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, and to underſtand of the great Mortality of Mankind is ordinary: to heare the Stones of that flaming and evaporating Hill <hi>Veſuvius</hi> neare the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>Naples,</hi> ſome yeeres paſt, who thruſt and belched from its bowells ſuch abundance of flame, ſmoake, and aſhes, with ſo much hurt, harme, and univerſall preiudice to the poore neighbouring Inhabitants, and to the Citizens of that flouriſhing City is
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:14355:5"/> every where publiſhed. I therefore willingly here omit the Relation of thoſe other remarkable &amp; memorable <hi>Earthquakes</hi> which have happened in ſundry parts, and divers Kingdomes of the World, which though they are confeſſed to be great, and horrid, and accompanied with the Mortality and Death of many perſons, yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the terrour thereof, the ſame hath not ſo much daunted and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mazed the hearts and courages of men as this now late <hi>Earthquake</hi> hath done, that happened the 27. day of <hi>March</hi> laſt, 1638. according to the <hi>Romane</hi> Account, about the Houres of 21. and 22. according to their Computation; and according to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> the 17. of <hi>March,</hi> 1637. and betweene Three and Foure of the Clocke in the After<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noone, being <hi>Saturday,</hi> and accounted the Feaſt-day of <hi>Saint Patricke</hi> the <hi>Iriſh Saint,</hi> in the Province of <hi>Callabria</hi> the Inferiour, part of the notable and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:14355:6"/> plentifull Countrey and Kingdome of <hi>Naples,</hi> which hath proved ſo uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſall a ſcourge to that Province, and unto that part of the Countrey, that the Tongue of Man cannot poſſibly recount the ſame, nor the leaſt part of the affliction which that miſerable people, the Inhabitants which are yet remaining thereabouts, have ſuffered: what ſudden and unexpected ſuffoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions by water did ſome endure! What openings of the Earth were ſeene, where the bodies of ſome were in part or in whole impriſon'd and ſtifled! how many are diſtraught with the terrour of the motions of the Hills and Mountaines! and how many ſlain and ruin'd with the fall of their Habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations and Manſions! how many he cover'd now in Death with that cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, which in Life defended them by Night and Day both from the <hi>Summers</hi> Sun and the <hi>Winters</hi> cold! how many were within doores ſlaine, before they
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:14355:6"/> could get out, and how many pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed in the fields ere they could re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne to their Cities and Houſes. The husband was aſwell unmindfull of his deareſt Wife, as the tender Mother was of her neareſt and dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt Children: The Maſter comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in vaine; and the Servant had no time to obey for feare of death: ſome ranne to the Houſe tops for ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and ſome to their Vaults and Sel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, yet both found their ruine alike: ſo that thoſe horrours this Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quake was accompanyed with, atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded upon the inhabitants both at home and abroad, both within their doores, and abroad in their fields; here was no leaſure for to ſend for a Prieſt, nor no time for adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the <hi>Sacrament;</hi> but onely that is in Chriſtian Charity to be belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, that every one beſeeched the pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and goodneſſe of the Almighty and moſt mercifull God for pardon for
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:14355:7"/> their ſinnes, who though he ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times in Iuſtice chaſtiſeth and ſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth, yet willeth notwithſtanding our totall perdition, and eſpecially of ſo many ſoules redeemed by the power of his precious blood, and by him ſo dearely loved.</p>
            <p>We then, like loving Children to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards ſo gracious and good a Father, with correſpondent ſincere affection, and pure hearts, ought alwaies ſo to live, as to be prepared for ſuch, or the like ſuddaine accidents and dangers, having recourſe to the footeſtoole of his mercy Seate, imploring there his aide, helpe, and protection, and flying and avoyding all occaſions of offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ſo gracious and mercifull a God, who is bent ever to puniſh the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, and to be merciful to the iuſt and penitent, thereby mitigating his iuſt wrath and vengeance, the which by how much it is for-flowed, is by ſo much the more to bee feared to increaſe.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:14355:7"/>
            <p> And now becauſe that from <hi>Meſſina</hi> in <hi>Sicilia,</hi> and from <hi>Coſſenſa</hi> in <hi>Apulia,</hi> the generality of theſe accidents is come unto us, I have thought it fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to nominate the principall and chiefe of theſe Cities, Townes, Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, and Signories which have ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd, and are ruin'd and deſtroyed by this ſo great and heavy a ſcourge, wereby every man may reſt truely and really ſatisfied with the certainty thereof.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="list_of_cities_and_castles_destroyed">
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:14355:8"/>
            <head>The names of the Principall Cities and Caſtles deſtroyed by the Earth-quake are theſe, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>THe <hi>City</hi> of <hi>Nicastero,</hi> which is wholly deſtroyed and ruined downe to the ground.</p>
            <p>The City <hi>of</hi> Monterane <hi>alſo whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſtroyed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The City <hi>of</hi> Nocera <hi>alſo wholly deſtroyed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The City <hi>of</hi> Caſtalione <hi>wholly deſtroyed: the Prince thereof</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:14355:8"/> 
               <hi>was here reſiding, whoſe corpſe are neither found alive nor dead, but ſome part and members of his Lady is found, and</hi> distingui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed <hi>from the reſt of her</hi> Ladies.</p>
            <p>The <hi>famous</hi> City of Coſſenſa,<hi>is the</hi> one halfe ruined <hi>and</hi> deſtroyed,<hi>with the</hi> Countrey-houſes therea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouts in the <hi>territory</hi> adjoyning; al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo the <hi>Palace</hi> of the Prince, the <hi>fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous</hi> Convent of the Jeſuites, and the much noted Convent of the <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puchin Friers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A great part</hi> of the City of Poala.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Balliwicke</hi> belonging to the Knights of <hi>Malta</hi> is wholy deſtroied and of a place of firme land, is become a ſtanding <hi>Lake</hi> and <hi>Water.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The City of <hi>Sancta Eufemia,</hi> wholly deſtroyed.</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:14355:9"/>
            <p> The City of <hi>Sancto Biaggio</hi> who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſtroied and utterly ruin'd.</p>
            <p>The <hi>great</hi> Caſtle of <hi>Billiato</hi> who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ruined and fully deſtroyed.</p>
            <p>The towne of <hi>Cattanzara,</hi> the halfe part or rather more deſtroied.</p>
            <p>The towne of <hi>Beggaria</hi> in part de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroied, and ruiued very much.</p>
            <p>The towne of <hi>Malerno</hi> in part de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroied, and the reſt much defaced.</p>
            <p>The towne of <hi>Pietra Mara</hi> wholy ruined and quite overthrowne.</p>
            <p>The towne of <hi>Arelo</hi> wholy rui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and alſo quite overthrowne.</p>
            <p>The towne of <hi>Bogliono</hi> with the territory thereabout, wholy deſtroied.</p>
            <p>The towne of <hi>Marecano</hi> wholy deſtroied, and utterly laid waſte.</p>
            <p>The town of <hi>Autilla</hi> wholy ruined.</p>
            <p>The town of <hi>Belcello</hi> quite ruin'd.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:14355:9"/>
            <p> The towne of <hi>Florolito</hi> deſtroied.</p>
            <p>The towne of <hi>Monte Sancto</hi> wholy ruined and quite left deſtitute of all.</p>
            <p>The towne of <hi>Monte Soro</hi> wholy ruined, and vtterly overthrowne.</p>
            <p>The towne of <hi>Fulgare</hi> the one half deſtroyed, the other part much ruin'd.</p>
            <p>The towne of <hi>Umbraciatico,</hi> the quarter part, or rather more ruined.</p>
            <p>The towne of <hi>Macdo</hi> but in part.</p>
            <p>The towne of <hi>Sancto Locido</hi> in part ruined, &amp; the reſt much defac'd.</p>
            <p>The towne of <hi>Rolian</hi> but in part.</p>
            <p>The towne of <hi>Poeſia Mala</hi> in part destroied, and the reſt much defaced.</p>
            <p>The town of <hi>Ogello</hi> in part ruin'd.</p>
            <p>The towne of <hi>Sancta Nicoſia,</hi> drowned, with the Neighbouring Country for five miles circute bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering upon the Seaſhoare, and many
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:14355:10"/> others of leſſer note and conſequence, not yet come to our true knowledge.</p>
            <p>In theſe <hi>Cities</hi> and <hi>Townes</hi> it is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported that there is <hi>Dead, Loſt, Drow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned,</hi> and <hi>ſuncke</hi> into the Earth, about fifty thouſand <hi>perſons,</hi> and that there was counted in theſe places twenty ſix thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Families great and ſmall: the ſaid Earth-quake having at that one inſtant of time ſpread it ſelfe for the circuite of three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcore and ten miles in compaſſe, and paſſed from <hi>Callabra</hi> over the Phare of Meſsina, to that Citty where the Belfree was ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, and fell upon the roofe of the principall Church thereof, breaking downe the ſame, with the death of many then at their devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the ſaid Church: The Arch-biſhop and Vicar of the ſaid City, with divers o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Church-men, who at that inſtant of time were walking neare at hand in a Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den belonging unto the ſame, were thereby freed and ſaved from that preſent danger, and that ſome alſo of the inhabitants of
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:14355:10"/> theſe above named Cities, ſaved them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves by flying away into the fields, and by many other ſtrange and unheard of acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents.</p>
            <p>Many other particular reports are ſpread abroad through <hi>Italy</hi> of this feareful, hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy, and ſuddaine iudgement, which wee will forbeare to nominate, deſiring Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God of his goodneſſe to bleſſe us, and preſerve us, and all men, from theſe, and the like ſuch dangerous incounters, Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
